I can smile, and murder while I smile
Richard III is a drama, war film directed by Richard Loncraine.
A murderous lust for the British throne sees Richard III descend into madness.
Though the setting is transposed to the 1930s, England is torn by civil
war, split between the rivaling houses of York and Lancaster.
Richard aspires to a fascist dictatorship, but must first remove the obstacles to his
ascension—among them his brother, his nephews and his brother's wife.
When the Duke of Buckingham deserts him, Richard's plans are compromised.
Richard III, played by Ian McKellen.
Queen Elizabeth, played by Annette Bening.
The Duke of Buckingham, played by Jim Broadbent.
Earl Rivers, played by Robert Downey Jr..
Lady Anne, played by Kristin Scott Thomas.
James Tyrrell, played by Adrian Dunbar.
Richard III is a 1995 film adaptation of William
Shakespeare's play of the same name.
Directed by Richard Loncraine, the film adapts the play's story and characters to a setting based on
1930s Great Britain, with Richard depicted as a fascist plotting to usurp the throne.
Ian McKellen portrays the title character, as well as
co-writing the screenplay with Loncraine.
The cast also includes Annette Bening as Queen Elizabeth, Jim
Broadbent as the Duke of Buckingham, Robert Downey Jr.
as Rivers, Kristin Scott Thomas as Anne Neville, Nigel Hawthorne as the Duke of Clarence, Maggie Smith as the Duchess of York, John Wood
as King Edward IV, Tim McInnerny as Sir William Catesby, and Dominic West (in his film debut) as Henry, Earl of Richmond.
Richard III premiered in Brazil on 20 August 1995, and was released in the United States on 29
December 1995, and in the United Kingdom on 26 April of the following year.
While unsuccessful at the box office, it received
critical acclaim, and won several accolades.
At the 50th British Academy Film Awards, it won the awards for Best Production Design and Best Costume Design, with
nominations for Best British Film, Best Adapted Screenplay, and Best Actor in a Leading Role for McKellen.
It also earned Oscar nominations for Best Art Direction and Best Costume Design, and McKellen
was nominated for a Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Drama.
The film explores themes of england, kidnapping, murder, king.
The tone is emotional.